<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>LiVE MAG!</title>
    <atom:link href="https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link>
    <link>https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19/</link>
    <description>Reviews</description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2020 19:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <generator>Wintersmith - https://github.com/jnordberg/wintersmith</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>End Run 19</title>
      <link>https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/end-run-19/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2020 19:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/end-run-19/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;January 1, 2019. The year started off with &lt;strong&gt;Bruce Weber&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Joanne Pagano Weber&lt;/strong&gt;‘s beautiful Alternative New Years Day poetry marathon—their last one in New York. We thank them for 25-years of devotion to community.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then my friend &lt;strong&gt;Carole Sorrel&lt;/strong&gt; hooked me up with &lt;strong&gt;Albert Scaglione&lt;/strong&gt;, the founder of &lt;strong&gt;Park West&lt;/strong&gt;, the largest gallery in the world according to &lt;em&gt;The New York Times&lt;/em&gt;. He wanted me to do a writing project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By February first I was on a yearlong whirlwind that would take me to Detroit, Atlanta, Orlando, Miami, Amsterdam, Belgium, and the Caribbean. I met several artists working with &lt;strong&gt;Park West&lt;/strong&gt; — &lt;strong&gt;Romero Britto, Lebo, Tim Yanke, Clare Sykes, Wyland&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;Glenn Marcus&lt;/strong&gt;. The father of Kinetic art, &lt;strong&gt;Yaacov Agam&lt;/strong&gt; did my portrait in Paris! And I renewed my acquaintance with &lt;strong&gt;Leslie Lew&lt;/strong&gt; who I knew from the bad old EV days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Albert was a lot of fun to follow, full of vim, vinegar, vitality, and veritas. I loved scribing his wit and wisdom and made many new friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Detroit Institute of Arts&lt;/strong&gt; gave a group of us a tour thanks to Albert’s sister &lt;strong&gt;Diane Pandolfi&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Ruben&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Isabel Toledo&lt;/strong&gt;‘s “Labor of Love” exhibit reimagined the museum with pieces they created that were inspired by the Institute’s collection and then placed in situ. I loved the surprise and incongruity — like strange doll figures in elaborate costumes sitting on a 300-year-old table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/end-run-19/tyree.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;pink junk sculpture on lawn&quot;&gt;
Jeff and Tyree Guyton, Guyton public art, Detroit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One morning the crew visited the &lt;strong&gt;Heidelberg Project&lt;/strong&gt; by artist &lt;strong&gt;Tyree Guyton&lt;/strong&gt;. The artworks sprawl across a once-vibrant section of Detroit in places where only a few homes are left. &lt;strong&gt;The Spotted House&lt;/strong&gt; is the most recognizable landmark in the section that stretches for several blocks.
Back in New York, I got to meet the visionary artist at &lt;strong&gt;Martos Gallery&lt;/strong&gt; for his opening. He’s continuing to build on his signature look, using a mix of fine art materials and recontextualized objects. “…Everything is connected to this one source of energy or this divine power.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the world of poetry and writing, the year brought several legends low. &lt;strong&gt;Steve Cannon&lt;/strong&gt;, founder of &lt;em&gt;A Gathering of the Tribes&lt;/em&gt;, opened his home and his heart to writers, artists, and musicians. He was feted by hundreds of friends and mourners in a second line parade that flounced and sashayed through the EV. “Love you madly.” &lt;a href=&quot;https://livemag.org/pages/issue_9.htm#cannon&quot;&gt;Live Mag # 9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steve Dalachinsky&lt;/strong&gt; turned off the light after reading for &lt;em&gt;A Book About Death&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;strong&gt;Ray Johnson&lt;/strong&gt;. Steve knew how to be a star. We send love to his partner of 40 years, &lt;strong&gt;Yuko Otomo&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Live Mag #2, 8,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://livemag.org/issue_16/steve-dalachinsky/&quot;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And &lt;strong&gt;John Giorno&lt;/strong&gt;, the great poly-artist who electrified audiences with his syle, slipped off while his show was up across the street at &lt;strong&gt;Sperone Westwater&lt;/strong&gt;. Giorno Poetry Systems enlarged the audience for poetry. “You got to burn to shine.” &lt;a href=&quot;https://livemag.org/issue_12/giorno.html&quot;&gt;Live Mag #12&lt;/a&gt; All sympathies to his partner, &lt;strong&gt;Ugo Rondinone&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Count your blessings, faithful readers, and shine.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>End Run</title>
      <link>https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/end-run/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2018 19:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/end-run/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Entering our 11th year, the editors would like to thank our sponsors, &lt;strong&gt;Howl Happening&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;La Mama&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;KGB&lt;/strong&gt;. And subscribers and contributors. Thanks to our readers, audience, and party-mates. Welcome to our new Associate Editor, artist and curator &lt;strong&gt;Kim Power&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New Orleans Poetry Fest&lt;/strong&gt;. What a gas! Live Mag! panel with &lt;em&gt;Poets Reading the News&lt;/em&gt; editors &lt;strong&gt;J Spagnolo&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Elle Aviv&lt;/strong&gt;, plus &lt;strong&gt;C&amp;amp;R&lt;/strong&gt; Press editor &lt;strong&gt;John Goslee&lt;/strong&gt; shared publishing and publicizing tips—DIY style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Came back to NYC with books from all over. Poetry of “brutal cartography” by &lt;strong&gt;Hossannah Ascuncion&lt;/strong&gt; from &lt;em&gt;Magic Helicopter&lt;/em&gt; (who also had &lt;em&gt;Noo Journal&lt;/em&gt;). Oracle flarings from &lt;strong&gt;Marc Vincenz&lt;/strong&gt;’s &lt;em&gt;Beautiful Rush&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Unlikely Books&lt;/strong&gt;. Tables included &lt;strong&gt;Lavender Ink/ Daialogos&lt;/strong&gt; with yummy translations of &lt;em&gt;Catullus&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;strong&gt;Joseph Bienvenu&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Trembling Pillow&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Western Kentucky U&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Iron Boot&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Chax&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Convulsive Editions&lt;/strong&gt; from Chicago. Shoutouts to &lt;strong&gt;Jonathan Penton&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;JS Makkos&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Paris Tate&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In big-time New Orleans style, there was a splendid second line parade for the much-missed &lt;strong&gt;Marthe Reed&lt;/strong&gt;, to whom the festival was dedicated. Saturday night at &lt;strong&gt;Siberia Lounge&lt;/strong&gt; rocked—with &lt;strong&gt;Douglas Kearny&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Tonya M. Foster&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Bruce Andrews&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Jesse Statman&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;Bill Lavender&lt;/strong&gt; topping it off.  Congrats to Festival founders Bill and &lt;strong&gt;Megan Burns&lt;/strong&gt;. Round three: April, 2019. Featuring &lt;strong&gt;Anne Waldman&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/end-run/mark.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;group at festival&quot;&gt;
Tonya M. Foster, her parents, and Mark Statman in New Orleans&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allen Hansen&lt;/strong&gt;’s paintings: Super show of powerful, finessed rawness, paintings that project the grotto, the cave, the soul of expression! “Atmosphere of Nothingness / or O” at the ever-fun &lt;strong&gt;Licthundfire Gallery&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Painter &lt;strong&gt;Amy Hill&lt;/strong&gt; makes the &lt;em&gt;NY Times&lt;/em&gt; for her &lt;strong&gt;Front Room&lt;/strong&gt; show of ironic, anachronistic portraits of idealized people in a disturbing utopia. Done to a tee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s one thing to live it. It’s another to remember it well. And it’s a whole ‘nother thing to write it down which &lt;strong&gt;Martha King&lt;/strong&gt; has gloriously done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Outside/ Inside  just outside the art world’s inside&lt;/em&gt;, new from &lt;strong&gt;BlazeVox&lt;/strong&gt;.
Romantic, uplifting, historic, sprawling, spunky and searching. So many cross currents of artistic lives, interactions with icons, told with clarity and catchiness. And insightful observations about class, gender, and ambition. What a valuable testimony! What scope. Martha brings it all home in this Romantic memoir /culture lab &lt;em&gt;tour de force&lt;/em&gt; portrait by a pioneer in the front line. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Touch down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JCW&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>At the Surprise Hotel</title>
      <link>https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/at-the-surprise-hotel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2017 19:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/at-the-surprise-hotel/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Barry Wallenstein’s latest collection of verse continues his pioneering foray into blending jazz and poetry. The poems are infused with a distinct musicality that’s reminiscent of raw bars and bayou blues. Stripped down emotions are buoyed by irrefutable truths. 
&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;bwbook.jpg&quot; class=&quot;book&quot; alt=&quot;cover&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
&lt;em&gt;At the Surprise Hotel and other poems&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;by Barry Wallenstein&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spdbooks.org/Products/9781564391414/at-the-surprise-hotel-and-other-poems.aspx&quot;&gt;Ridgeway Press&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wallenstein’s &lt;em&gt;oeuvre&lt;/em&gt; is truly performance poetry, incorporating the angst and cadences of jazz into bittersweet riffs that acknowledge our human foibles. Now, as a mature auteur, his work remains unjaded and authentic while tackling some stark realities. Instead of churning pity or bitterness, he recycles his reflections into insights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are four sections in the book, each with a distinct theme. &lt;em&gt;At the Surprise Hotel&lt;/em&gt;, (the title of the book as well as the first part), takes on a universal view of multiple characters, allowing us to see how our transitory, illusory perceptions and expectations often deceive us. The characterizations offer visual as well as auditory stimulation such as “she wears faux rhinestone tears” and “with lashes like the fins of fancy fish. In many ways these people are representative of certain types familiar to all of us as the writer elevates them into archetypes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the second part, &lt;em&gt;Events&lt;/em&gt;, short vignettes employ realism, surrealism and forthright honesty, to each us something new in each piece. Anyone trying to go beyond writing that is other than mere description or exposition will appreciate the difficulty of this accomplishment, particularly on such a consistent level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In “The Sommelier Says” we find what continues on in the world is often just a semblance of gentility: “The diners sip and smile again/ having put to sleep the threat of riots.” And a woman named Mina “is a marvel/ seeing into the hearts of people,” yet a frown is her natural expression. Emotions that are more intellectualized than felt, distance us from empathy. Distraction becomes a safer default position: “…you’d love the story but be too occupied to respond.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wallenstein warns us about our inability to be aware of ourselves, to look deeper, as in “Unprepared.” He reminds us that beyond our perceived stability “shadows drift and break/against the jagged stones.” And in “Murder in the Ranks,” we find many misdirected purposes masquerading as revolutionary  solidarity, the impetus being more about individual grievances than a common cause. There are many faux promises and pretentions to action, all a camouflage for loneliness and fears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Poetry Writer” and “Poetry Reader” respond to one another from two perspectives that are metaphorical for how we truly give and receive. In further companion pieces, Wallenstein shows us that poetry can subtly invade our senses, leaving lingering fragments like the refrain of a song.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part three, &lt;em&gt;Encounters&lt;/em&gt;, immerses us in the vagaries of romance. Wallenstein does this through observation rather than judgment. In “The Dispirited Lover” the telling lines “sweetened not by memory/ but by what memory denies” remind us to be wary of sinking into the comforts of melancholy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last section is aptly entitled &lt;em&gt;Departures&lt;/em&gt; in which Wallenstein examines mortality. He reminds us that we need to be vigilant about our presumptions. In “Tomorrow” he cautions, “Banish the thought that blocks the rhythm/ advancing age supports the pretense of wisdom.” As we nourish our solitude, particularly as we grow older, there is danger in that isolation: “Then they spoke about madness/  and how it thrives in exile.” We must not allow our &lt;em&gt;doing&lt;/em&gt; to obstruct our &lt;em&gt;being&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the touching elegiac poem “Taking Names: for Stephen Watson,” there are lovely ruminations on bereavement: “…this must have been an error/ to cross off my handsome friend/ in the middle of his everything.” In cataloging losses Wallenstein employs concise imagery that highlights the many ways we deal with death and the unavoidable: “—the train’s late; stormy weather on the platform/ standing on the tracks is a windy apparition.” &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the final poem of the book, “What Was, Was,” the last lines offer sage advice to live in the moment: “For every was in time’s fast memory/ an &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; trumps the was every time.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elizabeth Kley at CANADA</title>
      <link>https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/elizabeth-kley-at-canada/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31  Aug 2016 20:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/elizabeth-kley-at-canada/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The famous sonnet &lt;em&gt;Ozymandias&lt;/em&gt; by Percy Bysshe Shelley, reflects on a monumental sculpture’s eventual ruin and collapse. Elisabeth Kley’s exhibition appropriated the title to likewise challenge time, while exploring such diverse concepts as individuality, transience and tradition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Venetian opulence permeated the evocative installation of ceramic vessels, works on paper and two sweeping floor-to-ceiling panels. Classic motifs mined from Chinese calligraphy, Japanese design and Islamic ornamentation are reconfigured with fresh vision and relevance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Byzantine decorative patterns, Matisse’s textile depictions, and the bold style of Vienna’s Weiner Werkstaäte also come to mind. A decidedly urbane aesthetic unites the diverse mediums and epochs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ten ceramic works, which the artist identified as “flasks,” are made using the labor-intensive hand rolled coil-and-scrape technique. Kley, originally a painter and now also a ceramicist, has stated, “I’m not athletic enough to throw &amp;hellip; and it would have been too messy to work with water and wheel.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/elizabeth-kley-at-canada/kley.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ceramic&quot; title=&quot;Large Black Flask with Tree&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Large Black and White Flask with Tree&lt;/em&gt; (2015) is a bulbous shape covered with winningly rough symmetry and repetitive  undulating images. Truly objects of poetic emotion, sgraffito (scratchings) reveal a sumptuous underlayer of blue. Kley’s virtuoso mark-making generates a seductive energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The relief prints on Japanese paper depict stylized vases and urns, echoing Aubrey Beardsley’s pictorial tradition. Two sweeping, tessellated panels anchored the entire room, transforming the gallery into a dramatic installation &amp;mdash; part magic lantern, part tribal totem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kley is also known for her witty black and white portraits of artists, drag queens and writers. That same linear elegance appeared in this show’s bravado brushstrokes and interlaced forms. Within the parameters of a subtle and elementary palette, Kley’s painterly imagery is both sinuously delicate and powerfully direct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results are gorgeous, quirky creations that suggest that they are meant to hold something valuable and exotic. And they do &amp;mdash; they hold our attention, steadfastly. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Judy Pfaff</title>
      <link>https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/judy-pfaff/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 May 2016 15:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/judy-pfaff/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Somewhere After&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;At &lt;a href=&quot;https://communications.lafayette.edu/2016/03/09/judy-pfaffs-somewhere-after-featured-at-lafayette/&quot;&gt;Lafayette College&lt;/a&gt;, Easton, PA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judy Pfaff’s art requires several kinds of understandings. First, let’s think back to primordial installations &amp;mdash; cave drawings and dwellings, rituals in China and Southern Africa and Native American ghost dances in buffalo robes.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Think about Egyptian rulers who carried with them to the afterlife their slaves, dinner service, and fortunes. Think about caves, teepees, and tombs as original installation or performance spaces. Think about Tibetan Buddhists imagining the cosmologies of heaven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, let’s think about the histories of art &amp;mdash; about the periods, the decors, the painting and sculpture, and the layers of imagery up to the present, including Japanese and French cultures, and naïve artists like Henri Rousseau whose images fit so well between Picasso and Matisse. Add in geometric and abstract and conceptual kinds of art that somehow are universal and don’t exactly fit one time frame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further, let’s consider earth: its geophysicality &amp;mdash; mountains, rivers, oceans, sky, air; its flora and fauna, its vast array of trees living inside, on, and above the earth: nature in abundance &amp;mdash; its seasons, its moments of living and dying, its procreation and fruiting. Finally, there are the wonders of space and the imagination, of medicine and science. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, if you think in every direction and then create your own cosmology that both surrounds and frees its viewers, you have some idea of what Judy Pfaff is doing these days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; I missed seeing Pfaff’s early days at Holly Solomon’s in the 1960s, but I witnessed and wrote about her 1997 Andre Emmerich show on 57th Street, for which she totally transformed the space, including holes in walls and a huge dead tree with its roots suspended on chains in a middle gallery. Pfaff went on to create installations from Sao Paulo to Wyoming to the Barnes Collection in Philadelphia, where her fanciful version of Mrs. Barnes’ exotic garden is, perhaps, the only tribute anyone has ever paid to Mrs. Barnes. So each installation of Pfaff’s art is about entering worlds that have their own kinds of rhythms, symbols, objects, and colors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…each installation of Pfaff’s art is about entering worlds that have their own kinds of rhythms, symbols, objects, and colors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Somewhere After,” at Lafayette College in Easton Pennsylvania, is a creation myth. At the entrance is the upside-down roots of a dead tree decked out with colorful materials. It looks more like a chandelier since the roots seem to be branching and rising. The gallery space may be navigated in clockwise or counterclockwise directions.  Metal geometric straight “lines” overhead mark this maze and create sight lines which change altitude and then spiral onto the floor in a central black and white space which shows an Egyptian leader’s possessions &amp;mdash; his dogs, ducks, men, rams, lions, and his world. This black and white section shows a rigid hierarchy, inequality, and absence of color/life. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/judy-pfaff/pfaffW.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;sculpture installation&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back at the entrance, the upside-down tree roots are shallow. Perhaps they didn’t have enough room to grow or perhaps the tree died due to turbulent weather or old age.  Trees sometimes live longer than humans, but they, too, are part of the cycle of life and death. The roots are cloaked in extruded foam, an earthy eggshell, orange, and green mass that has basketlike forms of green, orange, and blue orbs in its arms and two spheres or primordial ooze at its base. This may symbolize earth’s wonders. A pendulum, which Professor Robert Saltonstall Mattison of Lafayette College calls Foucault’s Pendulum, is suspended over the roots, and two other pendulums are in another mass diagonally across the gallery.  Foucault’s Pendulum dates from 1851 and demonstrates earth’s rotation, yet is also the title of the Umberto Eco 1988 novel that is the antithesis of gravitational pull and, instead, about esoteric and conspiracy theories. The area diagonally across may be notions of heaven; it has a large Tibetan mandala on the floor and a plastic spiral that goes up. As in the entrance sculpture, orange, green and blue predominate. The ooze on top rises high and bursts into rainbows of color.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going around the room in both directions, orbs of vision abound. Some are highly distorted circles of Henri Rousseau’s world of plants, some are abstracted or figurative Tibetan mandalas, some are pure op geometries that seem to recede and advance into the space. In many, there are circles within circles that either collide, cross, or float together in concentric rings. Glitter and primal slime abound. There are immense rounds of roundness, multi-verses we can peer into, the ochre and green and white swirls become, in undulating variations, original gardens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exhibition title “Somewhere After” suggests an open narrative starting with the big bang &amp;mdash; or however you imagine the origins of the universe.  Pfaff’s many accomplishments and honors may be found on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.judypfaffstudio.com/&quot;&gt;her website&lt;/a&gt; and at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.art21.org/artists/judy-pfaff&quot;&gt;Art 21&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Judy Rifka</title>
      <link>https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/judy-rifka/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2016 20:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/judy-rifka/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Yard, Herald Square, NYC
Does Judy Rifka need to bother with the articulate justifications and cogent explanations that always accompany her latest creations? Not for this fully alive and eye-popping show&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, thanks to curator Gregory de la Haba. Elasticity reaches across decades of her art, revealing that it’s not a coincidence that Rifka has morphed through the years with ideas not flighty or fickle but ethereal and subject to necessary changes one might mistake for something else — if they didn’t know their stuff. People who do, know that her perennial voice, eye, and hand are deadly serious about mark-making and art-making by whatever means necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/judy-rifka/judy-yard.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;abstract&quot; title=&quot;Photo: Sylvie Ball&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is necessary in this show, is that the paintings &amp;mdash; mostly current works and examples from her rich history &amp;mdash;  are metaphors for her career: constantly shape-shifting, meta-morphosing and evolving vectors that swaddle turbulent energies like choppy waves atop an ocean secretly grounded by still waters murmuring deep below. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An ever-changing yet stable presence underlies undulating lines, strong shapes and sudden darts of color. The artist’s confident approach provides dependability against shifting cultural winds. Attitude embraces the wisdom of the ages or undoes it as needed. Techniques and tools, uniquely combined and arrived at intuitively, tell layered stories. Her stand, as always, is for a kind of holy but irreverent geometry. She plays with it but also sends it up or on its way, paying homage to and suggestive of all science with genuine Bezier curves evoking gowns, teepees or diagrams of ballroom dancing. Or all three moving with All-American defiance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judy Rifka points from within fake science toward dimensions reached for by predecessors. Dreaming of folds and hulls and Leonardo, she pictorially articulates Naum Gabo, Tatlin’s Tower, and Duchamp’s malic moulds and chocolate grinders &amp;mdash; all flattened by wild Fauvist slam dances.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Helga Kopperl</title>
      <link>https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/helga-kopperl/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2015 20:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/helga-kopperl/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;best-of-both-worlds&quot;&gt;best of both worlds&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beginning with depictions of Edo’s Floating World, Helga Kopperl has built a bridge of color and light across time and culture. She’s created a new space out of the old &amp;mdash; &lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; a space that incorporates the elegance, lyricism and vitality of the ancient Japanese art form and updates it. The resonant results conflate the past and present in unexpected and novel ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout the series, Kopperl’s unique interplay – between woodblock Ukiyo-e prints and bright, new digital techniques – achieves a surface tension that coexists with a suggested deeper bottom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her endeavor breathes new life into the geishas, samurais, kabuki actors, sumo wrestlers and other denizens of a bygone era. Kopperl appropriates calligraphy, designs, and motifs, transforming classic woodblock prints into startling new constructs. The bold transformations feel hauntingly evocative of former times, yet contemporaneous and reflective of our own society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/helga-kopperl/brighthouse.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;geisha in patterns&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;BRIGHTHOUSE&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 15 compositions in the series, the artist has chosen ideas from woodblock prints and digitally collaged them into impressive originals. The selected segments are shaped and then tweaked for color, tone and temperature. Sometimes white negative space looms, like the open passage in &lt;em&gt;MAGNOLIASHOULDER&lt;/em&gt;. In others such as &lt;em&gt;BORDERGATE&lt;/em&gt;, numerous transparent and opaque layers are piled in dense frontal heaps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like projections onto translucent screens, the images dance and weave over and under one another. In &lt;em&gt;BRIGHTHOUSE&lt;/em&gt;, a geisha stands, arms folded and resolute in a dreamy landscape of stains and patches. Complementary colors, scarlet and forest green, ripple around the figure. The folds in her dress enhance an atmosphere of mysterious landscape receding into depth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The surface gives way to a rich array of marks and forms as if the viewer is looking into a pond or a rainy puddle. Indeed, &lt;em&gt;MOONDIARY&lt;/em&gt; with its interlocking sea-green scallops, glimmers in refracted planes. Throughout the series, Kopperl achieves a surface tension that coexists with a suggested deeper bottom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;FLORABUNDA&lt;/em&gt;, however, the opposite sensation is achieved. The central images appear suspended above an opaqued background. Arbitrary shapes that resemble scimitars or eggs roll across a jumbled but gemlike landscape. A typically lush palette animates the dominant elements.  Orange and yellow decorative passages abut purple and turquoise floral designs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Richly patterned kimonos, flowers, fish and bonsai trees are all reconfigured into abstracted samples. Kopperl’s most compelling new configurations invite the viewer to explore unforeseen connections. Ultimately, sections of the collaged pieces are used almost like brushstrokes to create patterns. This is especially apparent in latter pieces of the series that exert swirling vortical pulls such as &lt;em&gt;LOOSENEDCLOUD, DAYWHEELS,&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;KABUKIGA&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;BLINDCHILD&lt;/em&gt; relates to an early Hokusai print, &lt;em&gt;36 Views of Mt. Fuji&lt;/em&gt;. The flat orientation of this print contrasts with the circular or concentric elements of the Floating World. Like whirling ribbons pegged to a center, crashing waves are sucked into a disappearing tunnel of spume and flowers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This circling whirlpool is a metaphor for our journey in life. Ghosts and blossoms from long ago are blended with desires and aspirations of the present. Kopperl rekindles delight from embers. In the process she creates contemporary phoenixes that are breathtaking to behold as they soar toward the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Suzan Batu</title>
      <link>https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/suzan-batu/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Mar 2015 20:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/suzan-batu/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A show of Suzan Batu’s easel-sized paintings creates a mood of worldly coquetry at &lt;a href=&quot;http://phatory.com&quot;&gt;The Phatory&lt;/a&gt;. It looks like the artist may have started with a straight and narrow method, and then took it south &amp;mdash; finding her true colors.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Batu, a respected painter with a mature career and a recognizable iconography, divides her life and work between New York and Istanbul. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The small paintings look portable in more ways than one. They offer a fresh perspective, a window for viewers (outsiders) into another culture. And it goes beyond her previous references to the calligraphy and sinuous curves of her Byzantine heritage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/suzan-batu/batu.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Installation view&quot; title=&quot;Photo: Eung Ho Park&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actual costume elements adorn these portrait-oriented works, which mirror the viewer up close at eye level. A few large color-coordinated feathers sprout from the would-be head. She’s also tucked a gleaming skirt of beads under the bottom edge of the painting. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bodies of the works, the paintings themselves, are compositions of reactive colors applied within hard-edge shapes that are perceptually mutable. Strings of these spherical, bead-like shapes meander to the fore and mutate in a riot of energy and abandon.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Batu has disrupted the rules of color and how it is supposed to create the illusion of depth. In these paintings, dull gray-greens sit smugly atop shadows of brightest lemon yellow. In the most complex and satisfying works, the shapes shift, arriving at the foreground as expanded squares or diamonds. They are layered and offset, like exploded 3D views. The colors defy the normal rule that warm colors come forward and cool colors recede. The rebellion and the resulting skewed perspective is both unsettling and dazzling. The paintings have monochrome backgrounds &amp;mdash; orange, red, green, or other &amp;mdash; and ethereal, velvety flat surfaces; yet they hold illusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The strings resemble novelty notions and costume jewelry. On another level, they are humanoids born of Batu’s previous lexicon of swirls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These new works pack a punch, for all their small size and intimate scale. They fit the tiny gallery space more comfortably than the large works in her last Phatory show. A more personable scale supports their friendly countenance and they sing a deeper song. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paintings sizzle, dressed for the dancehall. The outsized feathers and beaded fringes ultimately convince. Without the accoutrements, we would miss some of the fun. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, the paintings are presented on their own in a fitting catalog for the show, introduced with a Rumi poem. In a few lines, it helps locate these works as global citizens.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cat Town</title>
      <link>https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/sakutaro-hagiwara/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2015 19:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/sakutaro-hagiwara/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;“Soaked in tears.” How can you beat that? Sakutar&amp;omacr; Hagiwara (1886 — 1943) wrote this line early in his career. His penchant for the piteous remained his trademark. This volume of verse, including the title prose-poem novella, “Cat Town,” reveals a genius at joining image with sentiment.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; His writing produces a profound frisson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;hagiwara.jpg&quot; class=&quot;book&quot; alt=&quot;portrait&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
Portrait of Hagiwara, 1924
in &lt;em&gt;Cat Town&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;Translated by Hiroaki Sato&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nybooks.com/books/imprints/nyrb-poets/sakutaro-hagiwara/&quot;&gt;New York Review of Books&lt;/a&gt; 2014
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Lachrymose, his malaise drips like cold rain in the slums. It is worth noting (thanks to the translator’s preface) that Hagiwara did undergo serious bouts of instability. Otherwise, the overbearing morosity– “The Miserable Streetlight,” “The Riverside of Melancholy,” and “Odious Scenery” –becomes comical, though always formally rigorous and compelling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deeply analytic, he explains his technique in prose sections. He compares it to an electrical impulse capturing a rhythm. Alternately he compares it to a phobia or hallucination he is trying to put into words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lyric Romanticism pervades, populated with feelings of despair and gilded pathos. “It’s a shadowy gloomy district.” The countryside is “boring.” The wind is “screaming sadly.” We too would like to “sob in abandonment.” Some poems repeat key words like “sorrow,” “fear” and “melancholy” several times. Hagiwara weaves these dispositions into stark, surreal landscapes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In a field where bats swarmed&lt;br&gt;I watched a pillar of crumbling flesh&lt;br&gt;it trembled in the lonely evening darkness&lt;br&gt;smelled raw like dead-man’s-grass that flutters at a shadow&lt;br&gt;and was ugly as throngs of meat with maggots crawling on it.&lt;br&gt;Ah in this landscape that trails shadows&lt;br&gt;my soul clutches an itchy terror.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Passionate exhilaration pours through the tortured realms infusing the reader with a strange sensation. It’s as if one must perform an oxymoronic double register &amp;mdash; to admit the bracing beauty wrung from misery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his preface for &lt;em&gt;Blue Cat&lt;/em&gt; (1922) Hagiwara writes that he is only a shadow of a reflection of his disconsolation. He is but the “nightmare of a blue cat.” His kindred spirit could be Edgar Allen Poe and he was a great admirer of Baudelaire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An elegiac tone is sustained as feelings of agony are matched with macabre accounts of decay, rot, solitude and dejection. Hagiwara isn’t immune to joy and when he describes this emotion he reveals his deep love for life, providing relief and complexity to his oeuvre. “Spring Evening” begins:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How joyful to hold this close&lt;br&gt;the sensuous yet coquettish air&lt;br&gt;a twisted &lt;em&gt;rubber&lt;/em&gt;-like   rebounding young body…&lt;/em&gt;    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;  True to his doleful outlook, he ends: “signs of lust-melancholy sensuous sex / are like cherry blossoms that have bloomed.” In “Longing I Walk in a Crowd” he is carried away by the “merry wave.” Even here, he is predictably (and endearingly) “moved almost to tears.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Superbly translated, this collection provides an overview, including poems from Hagiwara’s first book, &lt;em&gt;Howling at the Moon&lt;/em&gt;, which was very successful when published in 1917. The startling imagery and clear descriptions were critiqued as being “true symbolist poetry written in Japan for the first time.” Innovative and uncanny, the writings remain shocking and unique. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adrian Matejka</title>
      <link>https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/adrian-matejka/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2014 20:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/adrian-matejka/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Although boxing holds no interest for me, I have always been intrigued by Jack Johnson, the first African American to be heavyweight champion. Adrian Matejka’s poetic paean to Johnson presents a portrait that beautifully captures the bravado, sexual energy and sophistication of an athlete whose 1915 victory sparked race riots. &lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;matejka.jpg&quot; class=&quot;book&quot; width=&quot;150&quot; alt=&quot;cover&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The Big Smoke&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.penguin.com/book/the-big-smoke-by-adrian-matejka/9780143123729&quot;&gt;Penguin Poets&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Divided into five sections, there is a loose chronology mirroring Johnson’s humble beginnings of a child of ex slaves. “Battle Royal,” the opening poem depicts a time when, “the man said only/ the last darky on his feet gets a meal”, and slave-owners decided boxing slaves to be more exciting then chained bears being savaged by dogs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Papa’s head shines like a wheel&lt;br&gt;with no tread. Beautiful man,&lt;br&gt;mi amore. He shines like Lake&lt;br&gt;Michigan in the July heat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I loved Matejka’s emphasis upon Johnson’s turbulent romantic life. There’s an inclusion of excerpts from the Department of Justice’s 1913 interview with one of Johnson’s white girlfriends, Belle Schreiber. “He was so large he almost blocked all the light from the hall.” As revolutionary and infuriating as Johnson’s athletic triumphs were to racist America, his living large lifestyle of bling, luxurious cars and Caucasian consorts led to a false conviction under the Mann Act, causing Johnson to be a fugitive for seven years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Johnson’s marriage to Etta Duryea, a society girl, ended with her suicide. “La Trovatore” memorializes Etta, ending with the lines, “Like realizing/ Etta’s still breathing, whispering/ a libretto on the heels of her last breath:/ You did this, Papa. You did this.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interspersing equally fascinating narrative voices, Johnson emerges as an American hero, volatile, flawed and a fabulist who wrote three autobiographies. “Ticket on the Titanic” explores Johnson and Etta’s attempts to buy tickets on the segregated luxury liner. “Of course, the color line kept me/ from fighting for Etta’s space on a lifeboat/ when the iceberg hit.” The concluding line resounds compassionately, “I would never dance the Eagle Rock/after all those people drowned.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Big Smoke&lt;/em&gt; is a poetry book for readers who might not read poetry. Like a great novel, the plot and characters are equally compelling. History transmutes to a lyrical legend, and Jack Johnson once again triumphs in &lt;em&gt;The Big Smoke&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jules de Balincourt</title>
      <link>https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/jules-de-balincourt/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jul 2014 20:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/jules-de-balincourt/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;True to the title of one of his paintings, &lt;em&gt;Land of Many Uses&lt;/em&gt;, Jules de Balincourt finds divergent scenes to convey a complex, sophisticated artistry. The 75 color plates in the book &lt;em&gt;Jules de Balincourt&lt;/em&gt; show the artist commenting on class, circumstance and connection with refined aloofness. &lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Cool by nature, he often depicts the cool. In one completely seductive vignette, a white yacht and its owner bob peacefully as white fireworks spill from a night sky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/jules-de-balincourt/balincourt.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;painting of boathouse&quot;&gt; 
&lt;em&gt;Utopia Tyrannique&lt;/em&gt;, 2010 oil on panel, 48 x 58 in. Courtesy Skira/Rizzoli&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These paintings from the last decade attest to de Balincourt’s diversity while examining the way we live as a species. Arenas, board meetings, and terrace parties teeter into Orwellian narratives. &lt;em&gt;The Boys Club&lt;/em&gt;, with its men in suits and ties, lauds success while hinting at injustice. Bright orange walls heighten a sense of both excitement and foreboding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Global Hunter&lt;/em&gt;, a roomful of animal trophies becomes a trope for the bad “good old days.” While the corridors of power are fair game for this artist, he rejects lampooning. The results are more nuanced, mixing beauty and ugliness in a seamless contest. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In examining how we live, the artist is especially conscious of our attempts to define space in terms of the collective. An interest in the pursuit of leisure (soccer stadiums, biking, boating) recalls classic artistic themes while &lt;em&gt;Naked Protesters&lt;/em&gt; humorously deflates the holiday atmosphere. Going further, de Balincourt depicts both “Insiders and Outsiders,” in a painting of a prison. In another piece, flood victims wade through a panoramic vista, evoking angst about our species’ predicted perils.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For an artist to be considered the “conscience” of his or her time, he or she must stir reactions to inequities. De Balincourt does this while maintaining a smooth, soothing sense. Andrea Scott writes in a preface, “de Balincourt’s gimlet eye is counterbalanced by equanimity.” Behind a patina of foreboding, one can find in these paintings, welcome places to rest the eye. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is ironic that street methods such as spray paint and stencils help make up the arsenal with which de Balincourt arrives at these pleasing paintings. He has forged a style that is resolute but baited. A disembodied touch lingers over the works, suspending them in a timeless vacuum even as they transport us to the border between utopia and dissolution.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Glen Goldberg</title>
      <link>https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/glen-goldberg/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17  Aug 2013 20:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/glen-goldberg/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Impulse and control stroll hand-in-hand in Glenn Goldberg’s gallery of icons. A dog stares back at you as you question it. A duck hangs in the air, as if between shots at an arcade.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; An insistent little man with big eyes scurries in stasis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Read between Icons and Screens: Whimsy, Utility, Sacrosanctity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;Other Places at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jasonmccoyinc.com/goldberg_exhibition_2013.html&quot;&gt;Jason McCoy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Punctuating these central images, Goldberg adds rows and rows of white dots. Initial washes and stains add subtle and seductive depth. The rich detail is a constant counterpoint to the overall compositions, drawing the eye in and out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goldberg has compared his rows of dots to stitching. Following the progression of repetitive marks, one senses the artist’s hand. Never too fussy but always focused, the technique transports the viewer back to the moment the paint was initialized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/glen-goldberg/gg.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;painting&quot;&gt; “painting”&lt;br&gt;&lt;em&gt;Other Place 18&lt;/em&gt;, 2013 acrylic on canvas, 16 x 12 in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like stitching, the paintings also recall other utilitarian and folk art genres; the decorative painting of porcelain, needlepoint, quilts, yard ornaments, Japanese screens, Shaker furniture and weather vanes. Stripes, both vertical and horizontal, add another register, suggesting ledgers and musical scores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A sensation of place and time or history permeates the sumptuous surfaces, lending the works precedence, as if they were born old. A curtailed palette adds to this agreeable association with antiquity. Simultaneously each one revels in freshness, brimming with impishly inscrutable novelty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blues and grays alternate with black and white. Wintry weather evokes coziness as well as adventure. Stray excursions into pale green and brown quietly amplify earthy materiality. Blotches arranged in loose patterns expand the works’ formal properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goldberg has referred to some of these textures as the skin of the painting. This artist’s physical connection to the paintings is particularly robust. His touch, both individualized and idiomatic, is critical to the works’ formidable integrity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While completely attractive without analysis, the paintings also activate contemplation of larger concerns. For Goldberg, something as simple as using a discarded brush can lead to a discussion of values and the undervalued. Each painting represents a record of memories and thoughts distilled. There is an authentic moral core here that Goldberg revels in unveiling. His compass bears close observation. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Judith Simonian</title>
      <link>https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/judith-simonian/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2013 20:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/judith-simonian/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;majesty-at-the-brink-of-chaos&quot;&gt;majesty at the brink of chaos&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.edwardthorpgallery.com/&quot;&gt;Edward Thorp Gallery&lt;/a&gt; Chelsea, NYC&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evoking the brushwork of John Singer Sargent, and the spirit of late Philip Guston, Judith Simonian is the fever-dreamed salon painter of J.G. Ballard’s dystopic High Rise interiors.  Simonian produces ambitious, head-spinning re-conceptions of tabletop still-life, interior, and landscape painting for the 21st century as Matisse did for the 20th century. Though she is no newcomer to the art community, the month May marked the first opportunity to see an entire solo show of 16 acrylic on canvas paintings ranging from a foot to 7 feet wide. &lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/judith-simonian/judyS.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;painting&quot;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Multicolored Carpet&lt;/em&gt;, 2013. Acrylic on canvas, 72 x 64 in. Courtesy of Edward Thorp Gallery&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In quantum physics the “Many Worlds” theory proposes that there is not one universe, but many, in parallel, offering alternatives to everything–simultaneously. Adept at making harsh ruptures and jump-cuts in space, time, and subject, Simonian has the ability to convey the complexity of “Many Worlds.” William Burroughs explained that “when you cut into the present, the future leaks out.” Simonian’s “leaks” of the future include surprising parts of the past and present. Unpredictable elements of unknown eras and areas such as mountain peaks, lounge chairs, ship prows, carpets, and fleshy, flashy, iridescent fish all co-inhabit the compositions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Multicolored Carpet&lt;/em&gt;, a large work completed earlier this year, Simonian allows a viewer to look into the thought process–as one image supplants another. In the upper left corner, a small, framed profile of a man’s face looking at a woman with her arms up offers a cue. An enriched grisaille interior at twilight is sketched in broad loose brushstrokes and drizzly washes that bleed into one another. A modernist, slatted bench with large plants recedes from the front left while a simple streamlined sofa fills the indeterminate background on the right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scene is interrupted by a much more vivid, full color image hurtling into the center of the — just as a strong memory supplants one’s view of any immediate but less compelling “real” environment one is in.  This color image is drenched with strong afternoon sun casting traceries of shadow through a circular, lens-like glass-top table. Shadows of the table and the mullions of an unseen window splay across a white carpet patterned with lively-colored biomorphic shapes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the lower right, small ghostly sketches of a two-handled (armed?) mug and another female form with uplifted arms shimmer and disappear as if small arrested thoughts stubbed-out liked half-smoked cigarettes. Tiny brilliant ultramarine flecks dance across the canvas like the flickering floaters one encounters in one’s eyes after having looked too long or hard at a brilliant scene. This brilliant scene is more packed with memories of images than with immediate life, itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aware of history, yet not bound by theory, Simonian parses out the universe directly with her paint. Her tough compositional and color decisions result in works with a rugged, feral beauty. Just as an animal will coldly, calmly chew off its own leg to escape from a spring trap, time and again this artist will “chew off” or destroy part of her own beautiful composition in order to escape the trap of any sort of conventional resolution. And, she invariably returns to invent something shockingly different and better to replace it. She is willing, as few others are, to cut off obviously gorgeous passages at the knees or to shift color palettes from warm and luscious to acrid and acidic to lurid and florid all on the same canvas. These paintings rest magisterially at the brink of chaos. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Marlene Tseng-Yu</title>
      <link>https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/marlene-tseng-yu/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2012 20:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/marlene-tseng-yu/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.acagalleries.com/past-exhibitions/year-2012/marlene-tseng-yu-forces-of-nature/&quot;&gt;ACA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;communing-with-the-elements-yu-s-irrepressible-vision&quot;&gt;communing with the elements: Yu’s irrepressible vision&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Artist Marlene Tseng Yu is unique in her ability to merge the traditions of her ancestral Chinese culture with Modernism. Her exuberant and vibrant paintings reflect Abstract Expressionist practices while offering the viewer a narrative that has its nexus in nature. Her new show at ACA Galleries, called &amp;#8220;Forces of Nature,&amp;#8221; includes work going back from 1971 to the present. &lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/marlene-tseng-yu/marlene.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;painting&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;em&gt;Molten Lava&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A deep bond with the physical world has informed Yu&amp;#8217;s metaphysical vision for over four decades. She organizes ineffable scenes that suggest a correspondence in the natural world. For instance, in &lt;em&gt;Molten Lava Park&lt;/em&gt;, the title tips us off. A black and white center seems to be heaving up from an explosive background, like lava pouring out of a vent in the ocean. Blocks of ridged grays seethe under a magpie crust of black and white. Vertical rhythms recall the crystalline forms of lava chimneys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yu varies her marks considerably, adding to the perception of artistic control over phenonmenological chaos. Amorphous clouds and fiery washes contrast with concise shards and irregular recessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within her lexicon, an overall impression of activity is maintained. In &lt;em&gt;Sunken Treasure&lt;/em&gt; the ridges become tighter and are crossed by rows of brown and jade (like the bands of color in a turkey&amp;#8217;s tail feathers or the accretion lines of an oyster shell). Once again, magpie sections resembling the random markings of a dairy cow, swell to the surface, this time pushing the central image back instead of forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the shell-like facets, ruby and scarlet forms emerge, resembling the wavering tentacles of a sea anemone or the jeweled flanges of a vagina. These divergent interpretations attest to the artist&amp;#8217;s skill at conveying nature, recalling Georgia O’Keeffe’s metaphoric and compositional mastery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s more, Yu activates the spiritual component that we seek in nature. Whether invoking the cosmic or the microscopic, the constant flux of matter finds eternal equilibrium in Yu’s powerful expressions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &amp;#8220;the age of mechanical reproduction,&amp;#8221; the act of pure painting is cause for celebration. Marlene Tseng Yu is a pure painter. She provides an invaluable link to our collective comprehension of what can be intuitively ascertained with the mind&amp;#8217;s eye.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joyce Melander-Dayton</title>
      <link>https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/Joyce%20Melander-Dayton/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2010 19:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/Joyce%20Melander-Dayton/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.therymergallery.com/gallery/?id=58&quot;&gt;The Rymer Gallery&lt;/a&gt; in Nashville&lt;br&gt;Aaron Payne Fine Art in Santa Fe&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.junekellygallery.com/dayton/&quot;&gt;June Kelly Gallery&lt;/a&gt; in Soho, New York&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;parallel-universes-converge&quot;&gt;parallel universes converge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;in-a-triple-gallery-mid-career-retrospective&quot;&gt;in a triple gallery mid-career retrospective&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking back over the works selected for Joyce Melander-Dayton’s mid-career retrospective, three stages can be articulated. The artist moved from objectivist juxtapositions to a non-objectivist affair with pure shapes and organic textures. The work representing twenty-five years has completely metamorphosed–and revealed key conceits in doing so. &lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/Joyce%20Melander-Dayton/the_little_things.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;painting&quot;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The Little Things&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Always interested in patterns and pairings, Melander-Dayton developed a highly polished technique of rendering shoes, bowls, bells and other tokens. A 1993 acrylic and pencil work &lt;em&gt;Dead Dog&lt;/em&gt; depicts a row of tightly drawn Monopoly charms—a thimble, a hat, a wheelbarrow and so on. The cast figures line up in a row on a white bar superimposed over a rich, washy brown atmosphere. The word GO in red appears austerely below them. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The visual phenomena of the objective world are, in themselves meaningless; the significant thing is feeling.&lt;/em&gt;  Kasimir Malevich&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fine-tuning the balance between realism and abstraction, Melander-Dayton painted a thin white X across the entire canvas, from corner to corner. This earlier composition, with its symmetric mix of charged imagery and neutral content, presages the artist’s evolving concerns. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cumberland Blues&lt;/em&gt;, from 2002, synthesizes the realist / abstract divide into an iconic impression of fluidity. A swaying blue line runs down the left side of a canvas, suggesting the Cumberland River. A vertical black line separates it from a column of circular shapes and outlines. These roundish shapes are like bubbles or the heads of a crowd. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the oval shapes are painted and some are woven onto the linen surface with wool. White faces, black balloons, and half-painted blue eggs in different sizes–all rise from a scored, scarred scrum of overlapping under painting. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a dialogue between the two sides, time appears endless on the left and instant on the right. The serenity of the broad blue band undulating down through space is countered by an insistent, jostling ascension. The river’s mighty scope is reframed as the sum of its component drops. Melander-Dayton’s play between forms leads to ultimate syntactic shifts where abstraction becomes metaphoric.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pulling from her childhood experiences in Asia, the more recent work extended an artisanal approach. Elements of folk art, craftwork and &lt;em&gt;feminine&lt;/em&gt; arts (like embroidery) have been amplified, upsetting notions of hierarchy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rondo&lt;/em&gt; from 2009, breaks free from a framed presentation. A slew of curved triangular shapes (39 in all) were arranged on the wall, bridging a corner at the Rymer Gallery exhibition. The notion of fluidity animated the modular array. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like stones in a stream, the units were related by their smooth contours and marine hues. Varying in size, the labor-intensive pieces included wool, cotton and beads on gator board. Built-up edges were elaborately woven. Looping lines of thread ran across the sea-blue surfaces. Interlocking shapes rose and submerged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Melander-Dayton’s triangular forms suggest palettes, sewing hoops or guitar picks. In her latest work at Aaron Payne Gallery, she has focused on this distinctive form. &lt;em&gt;Archipelago&lt;/em&gt; extends the concept of ??Rondo??. Like islands, eight shapes sprawl across the wall. Their sangria bubinga burl veneer recalls souvenir art painted on wood. The surfaces include silk, wool and beadwork patterns that evoke an Aboriginal aesthetic, echoed in the boomerang configurations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last few years, Melander-Dayton has mastered a stand-alone sculptural strategy and &lt;em&gt;Canyonlands&lt;/em&gt; leaves the wall altogether. This new work with its cinnamon, teak and salsawood coloring, reflects the Santa Fe terrain of the artist’s home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In what could be an expression of geology, one triangle shape is mounted sidewise atop another. Onto the polished wooden surfaces of these two units, mimetic triangle shapes and outlines are overlaid. While resolutely enigmatic, they can suggest stylized hills or clouds or even as a mouth and eyes. However, the potential transfer from landscape to figurativism remains suspended in illusionary abstraction. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years Melander-Dayton has diligently distilled a personal lexicon based on iteration and gesture. The new plateau she has reached is grounded in the postmodern practice of attention to process. Her dynamic balancing act could be described as isometric, from the Greek term for &lt;em&gt;having equal measurement&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an artist, Melander-Dayton finds lilting congruence between objective and non-objective–between abstract and representational. Her highly individualistic phrasing is poised and compact. The universal and the personal are fused in her lyric, liberating vision.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dorothy Iannone</title>
      <link>https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/dorothy-iannone/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14  Aug 2009 14:25:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/dorothy-iannone/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;see-her-roar&quot;&gt;see her roar&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I had an overwhelming reason to change my life completely, being in love was the first and only thing,” Dorothy Iannone told me on the phone from her Berlin home. Four decades ago, this grand passion propelled the self-taught American artist Dorothy Iannone (b. 1933) to create an expatriate life with her lover, the influential Swiss-German avant-garde artist Dieter Roth (1930-1998). Documenting their love affair, Dorothy took Dieter as her inspiration and muse. “The two of us became the stars of my work,” Iannone said. Her highly personal and poetic artwork was the subject of concurrent shows at the New Museum and Anton Kern Gallery in Chelsea this year. &lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/dorothy-iannone/iannone.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;painting of woman&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the early 1960s, the Boston-born Iannone has made intensely intimate and original paintings, drawings, figures and mixed media pieces. New Museum curator Jarrett Gregory, inspired by seeing Dorothy’s work in the 2006 Whitney Biennial, put together a beautiful, if small, show of Iannone’s work from the ’60s and ‘70s, including her iconic 1976 book &lt;em&gt;The Icelandic Saga&lt;/em&gt;. “Dorothy is a liberated human being and makes work from her heart, which gives her practice an immediacy that is uncommon and refreshing,” Gregory said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honoring the past and embracing the future she was filled with love for everyone. –Icelandic Saga&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Included in the New Museum show are Ianonne’s early “People Series,” painted wooden figurines depicting Charlie Chaplin, a pugilistic Norman Mailer, bare-breasted geishas and Jackie Kennedy. Genitals hang casually from trousers, erections exaggerated. These early figurines embody Iannone’s lifelong celebration of sexuality as integral to life. For “Access All Areas,” an upcoming group show at Galerie Max Hetzler in Berlin, Iannone is again devising cut-out figures. “Somehow I got the wish to make more cut-outs, with the text integrated, maybe at the bottom,” Iannone said. “The scenes are mostly from films I have seen over the years.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iannone’s large paintings depict her and Roth in formally sensual unions, inspired by great romances, such as Shakespeare’s Anthony and Cleopatra. Female and male are portrayed as equal adventurers. A reduced and powerful palette highlights tribal details, while referencing an early Pop sensibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The African motif appears as a trio of ebony and gold shields in &lt;em&gt;I Begin To Feel Free&lt;/em&gt; (1970), and again via balanced tribal decorations in &lt;em&gt;I Am Whoever You Want Me To Be&lt;/em&gt; (1970). Both couples depict a pelted Roth balanced by Dorothy’s armless Pop figure. Her colors and free mix of image and text remain as international as they are contemporary. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the Anton Kern Gallery are nine more works, including paintings made from earlier sketches. Later pieces like &lt;em&gt;On the Continuing Journey&lt;/em&gt;, with its erotic mandala, are suffused with Buddhist equanimity and reflect a spiritual synchronicity. Her imagery, consistent in detail and line, has grown more refined in her present work. Breasts which ended in bulls-eye nipples now feature decorative corollas. Opulently adorned surfaces are reflective of an expanded consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Male and female equality remains constant. Two works from 2009 embody a psychedelic energy. &lt;em&gt;Tickles My Fancy&lt;/em&gt;, a gouache-and-ink on board, features extravagant adornment illustrative of an expanded consciousness, as does &lt;em&gt;Metaphor&lt;/em&gt;, with its silken bondage cord and tattooed text, reading “sometimes you must also submit.” Instead of the usual autobiographical raven tresses, this odalisque is blonde and buxom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dorothy’s gentle, hypnotic voice echoes through the gallery, the sound of the audio CD included in the 1972 piece &lt;em&gt;Dinner Box&lt;/em&gt;. The painted box is crowded with a haunting cast of revelers. Iannone, who has been censored and under-appreciated in her native America, is enjoying a renewed interest and enthusiastic appreciation of her profoundly personal vision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New Museum curator Massimiliano Gioni calls her “our great lady of irreverence.” Dorothy studied literature, but says that “I just wanted to make art. I just kept doing it. I was doing what I wanted to do.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A version of this article first appeared in artnet.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mickalene Thomas at Lehman Maupin</title>
      <link>https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/mickalene-thomas/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Apr 2009 20:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/mickalene-thomas/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;bringing-bling-to-the-art-game&quot;&gt;bringing bling to the art game&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;America has three super myths &amp;mdash; the frontier, the racial mix and the belief that anybody can be somebody. We’re informed and fascinated by all three. Their intersection is our most potent avenue to metaphor and metamorphism. Mickalene Thomas is a triple-crown contender in this arena.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;The National Portrait Gallery acquired her silkscreened portrait of Michelle Obama. This first solo exhibition in New York at Lehmann Maupin (she had a one person show at Rhona Hoffman Gallery in Chicago) calls for busting out the bubbly. A big, brassy blockbuster, it will knock your knickers off, whether you like it or not. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thomas builds on traditional representations of women in the arts and grafts them to modern media and the appurtenances of soft porn, pop culture and Blaxploitation films of the 70s. But her quotes are dichotomous: half pastiche and half homage… half showgirl – half earthy matriarch. Her figures exude strength and inner assurance even while the artist appropriates questionable sources of authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;vodun-and-rhinestones&quot;&gt;vodun and rhinestones&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mickalene told me that she didn’t gravitate to art at an early age. “I didn’t think I could draw well. I was into sports in high school.” She did attend after school programs that her mother enrolled her in. These programs had craft elements that may have influenced the use of nontraditional materials such as the rhinestones and thrift store get-ups her models wear. In addition to formal art training at Yale, the artist also studied Aboriginal art and Vodun flags. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thomas has transferred some of the flash of modern day celebrities in sports and music and brought the glittering bling to her art. She’s not the first or only one to use rhinestones in paintings (Rhonda Zwillinger, Chris Ofili) but she has carved out a singularly attractive signature style. And now she’s upped the ante by including Federovsky crystals in the newest work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/mickalene-thomas/mickalene.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;woman on couch&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the main gallery, four large portraits of African American females dominate the space. Posed in dramatically seductive and over the top poses with historical precedence, the women radiate sensuality, sass and volume.
The submissive, reclining female, or odalisque, is a somewhat thorny (and corny — think saloon nude) act in art history but it is definitely a perennial. And as the great actors know, you have to risk being corny. Every queen comes with a fool. This artist keeps the jest in majesty. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thomas begins with a photo of a woman in a room. Often her subjects strike subtly contorted expressions of horizontals and diagonals. Vibrant throw pillows, couches with competing patterns and wood paneling form a tropical mise en scene in which the subjects bloom. Thomas then makes collages based on the photos that are used as studies for the paintings. Each reproduction adds a layer of illusion and mystique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;naughty-n-nice&quot;&gt;naughty ’n’ nice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A playful audacity complements the sumptuous physicality in &lt;em&gt;Naughty girls (need love too)&lt;/em&gt;. As the title implies, Thomas balances her siren’s edge with grace and vulnerability. A woman in thigh high “hooker boots”, raises up horizontally off a couch by one leg and one elbow in a highly manipulated and suggestive pose. The boots and outfit are studded with numerous shiny rhinestones. Crystalline points accentuate the hair and face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The odd angles of the woman, her head dipping down and her breasts thrust up, are integrated into the overall activity. In contrast, a midnight blue miniskirt and dark skin isolate the figure and project it forward. The wooden panels of a 70s era rec room reflect the cultural milieu of Thomas’s youth and are also autobiographical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This autobiographical aura complements the art historic associations that are apparent in &lt;em&gt;Mama Bush: One of a Kind Two&lt;/em&gt;. Manet’s &lt;em&gt;Olympia&lt;/em&gt; is updated in this twelve-foot wide rhinestone, acrylic and enamel painting on a panel. Blocked color recalls Jacob Lawrence’s bold exaggeration within a representational framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mama…&lt;/em&gt; peers at us over her shoulder with a “come hither” look. A riot of fabrics on the couch evokes interiors by Bonnard or Vuillard. A fractured floral pattern drapes the couch, shimmering with hundreds of black, white and grey beads and clear crystals, emphasizing a powerful, abstract subtext.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;dramatic-daring&quot;&gt;dramatic daring&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mama Bush is apparently a code name for Mickalene’s mother. In addition to this nude, a simple seated painting of Mama Bush in a dramatic black and red dress exudes a different kind of daring. Here smoldering elegance and dignity crackle into flame. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a new direction for Thomas, a video of Mama Bush posing for the camera is presented beside a portrait, creating a technical diptych. Eartha Kitt songs add a final touch, both personalizing the sitter and monumentalizing her “Everywoman” aspect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Returning to the multi-panel format of her “FBI/ Serial Portraits” and “America the Beautiful” series from last year, she has expanded to a 40 panel painting. &lt;em&gt;A-E-I-O-U and Sometimes Y&lt;/em&gt; presents expressive faces in rows, photo booth style. Most faces are limited to two tones and reference the simple silk screens of Andy Warhol. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ten full color portraits activate the grid, giving it the conductive resonance of &lt;em&gt;Broadway Boogie Woogie&lt;/em&gt; by Mondrian. This extra association also reclaims the African-American heritage of boogie woogie and its blues roots. 
In addition to the iconic portraits of females, Thomas previously created a series of “Big Cats”. The feline images, while sleek, emanate menace. They are beautiful but remain wild… easy but ready to spring. Likewise, Mickalene Thomas’s compelling oeuvre evokes both danger and domesticity. She forces us to confront banal stereotypes and rewards us with complex archetypes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on a legend that Thomas must appreciate, Benetta Jules-Rosette and Njami Simon wrote in &lt;em&gt;Josephine Baker, the Icon and the Image&lt;/em&gt;, “Even contemporary pilgrims, whose quest is secular rather than religious, seek to be close to icons and glorified objects of value so that some of the magical power will rub off on them.” Go, pilgrim.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kim Keever</title>
      <link>https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/kim-keever/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2008 19:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/kim-keever/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ktfineart.com/artists/kim_keever/&quot;&gt;Kinz, Tillou and Feigen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;nature-calls-in-kim-keever-s-landscape-photos-of-submerged-dioramas&quot;&gt;Nature calls in Kim Keever’s landscape photos of submerged dioramas&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human nature is part of nature but is also painfully apart from it. We are always aware of our separation from the innocence and sanctity we associate with nature. Art tries to address that longing, most especially in representational, landscape paintings. &lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Landscape as a genre may seem out of place in the modern world, but it was top dog in the days of the Hudson River school when America’s character was being forged by the notion of a vast and endless wilderness. Contemporary landscape still claims its painterly heroes like April Gornik and Rackstraw Downes. Celebrated photographic practitioners of landscape include Emmet Gowan, Richard Misrach and Victoria Sambunaris. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there are photo manipulators and photographers building sets like Thomas Demand and Didier Massard. It is this latter category that Kim Keever is roughly aligned with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/kim-keever/keever.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;landscape photo&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;em&gt;Forest 83c&lt;/em&gt;, C-print. Courtesy Kinz and Tillou&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This November at Kinz, Tillou and Feigen, landscape is getting some new attention. In addition to showing Hudson River School paintings in collaboration with Godel &amp;amp; Co. Fine Art, Kim Keever’s latest photographs of his models are on view. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s an ironic update on the venerable landscape tradition, because at first blush Keever’s photographs read as throwbacks. Big and billowy, cloud-filled vistas of a pristine corner of the world, they relate directly to Albert Bierstadt, Thomas Cole and Frederick Church. Uncut versions of Eden, no sign of pesky humans disrupts the preternatural awe. Only rocks, plants and atmosphere inform these regions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to tell that these scenes are not actual places. But in fact, they are dioramas that Keever has constructed in a big fish tank and photographed. Only Andres Serrano has thus far made it by submerging subjects (remember &lt;em&gt;Piss Christ&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;symphonic-pitch&quot;&gt;symphonic pitch&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keever assembles his dioramas using twigs, rocks and plaster that he sculpts to resemble mountains, cliffs and boulders. He also loves to visit the model railroad store where he finds convincing plastic plants for his compositions. Clouds are cotton placed behind the tank. Lighting effects amplify the illusions. Much of the light’s delectable hues are achieved by pouring pigment into the water and letting it disperse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By reframing the concept of the natural world, Keever has restored a sense of wonder to it. His depictions of environments ring with the exalted pitch of a full on symphony. Here, the artificial engages reality through a hyper-contextuality. Time and space are conflated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are not old paintings of real places although they conjure past masters. They are instead inventive portals of desire. They are addresses of the imagination where we can examine philosophical conundrums about what we worship and why. They are exceedingly lovely and over the top. And that works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As leavening, a graceful distance from beauty is maintained by the faint scuzz marks that Keever leaves on the fish tank’s inner walls. This secondary surface of ethereal slime adds a requisite grunginess to the product while highlighting the process. It also adds the illusion of the passage of years, implying survival and thus imparting a sense of greatness to the artwork. All of these commingling associations blend together to form a warm, but sharp focus. The closer you look, the more pleasing the assembly of visual “information.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;virgin-allure&quot;&gt;virgin allure&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Forest 83c&lt;/em&gt; evokes a delightfully primal feeling with its lure of virgin territory. Layers of cloudbanks bulge around an emerging moon. Its effulgence is perfectly located between a couple of tall pines on the left and a leafy giant on the right. As in Turner’s atmospheric pyrotechnics, the sky is unabashedly glorious. Layers of cascading clouds are bathed in robin egg blue, periwinkle and lilac, indicating a transient time like dawn or sunset. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bewitching hour is played up. Everything is heightened to the point of a silent crescendo. A placid stream recedes down thicket-dense banks. Gnarly branches posit a surge of ragged silhouettes against the immense curtain of evening as it ascends. Our eye is lead to the diffuse horizon that pledges a rendezvous with the sublime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fog grips a ridge in &lt;em&gt;Wildflowers 52i&lt;/em&gt;. The mist has opened enough for us to see a throng of bright flowers filling the foreground. Tropical in their brilliance, they are spotlighted, creating an animated intimacy. They communicate an inviting sense of purity, elevation and anticipation. They stir us. In the distance a mountain looms through a break in the clouds, beneath a promising patch of blue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conceptually, Keever has re-framed our appreciation of wilderness areas by mythologizing them. Again, the artist leads us to contemplate an ideal–a transcendent place we would really like to see.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alejandro Almanza Pereda</title>
      <link>https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/alejandro-almanza-pereda/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Oct 2008 20:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/alejandro-almanza-pereda/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Fan and the Shit&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.magnanmetz.com/exhibitions/alejandro-almanza-pereda-the-fan-and-the-shit&quot;&gt;Magnan Metz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like accidents waiting to happen, Alejandro Almanza Pereda’s work challenges structural integrity as it engages the concepts of stability, risk and danger. In a second show at Magnan Emrich Contemporary, the artist has fine-tuned his iconoclastic, sculptural assemblages. Moving away from found objects and furniture, he builds on groundbreaking shifts in materials first expressed in Jeff Koons’ fish tank and Haim Steinbach’s commercial items displayed on shelves. Pereda’s new show extends his earlier balancing acts while rounding off some rough edges. &lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lighting fixtures are still part of Pereda’s trademark vocabulary as are construction tools. As previously, objects are re-contextualized in startling combinations and height is examined, as works are precariously elevated and placed “out of reach.” &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In “It is for our own safety”, the cachet and elitism of red velvet ropes are telescoped and spoofed at the same time. By making the metal poles 10 feet high, Pereda amplifies the materiality while rarifying the vision. Above us, the seductive ropes sequester a sparkling chandelier. The silver, red and crystal are imminently appealing, evoking class and exclusivity and exuding a faux fairy tale aura. Yet a visceral feeling of smallness, rejection and insecurity falls on the viewer as he or she walks between the poles and under the chandelier. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of Pereda’s muscle comes from his ability to symbolically charge the atmosphere and mirror emotional states. Nowhere is this more apparent than in the central work of this two-part exhibit. Based on the game of Rocks, Scissors and Paper, items are ensconced in a glass grid. Shiny metal clips hold the transparent squares and rectangles together. Evoking domesticity, industry, panic, violence, life and stagnation, the different things inside create a schismatic dialogue. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the objects are repeated. Six paper globes glow, each lying on its side with wires running up and into the ceiling. There are five axes emblazoned with the logo TRUPER. A cone of confetti… some lumps of coal… two bonsai trees… five cinder blocks… nail clippers… a law book… a discourse is opened between these disparate entities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a top compartment a glop of cement has smeared the sides and hardened in the center. Characteristically, Pereda has inversed the balance and put the heaviest part on top of a seemingly fragile construct. In one of the bottom cubes, an open tall boy in a brown paper bag completely deflates the elevating concept of a vitrine. Usually, vitrines house esteemed relics not empty beer cans. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Witty and irreverent, the piece is also aesthetically intriguing with its rhythms and reflections. At the heart of it all is a wad of fifty-dollar bills. An axe in glass communicates emergency as well as temptation. This is not a passive display in the sense that it both mirrors anxiety and impulse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weight is conflated with light in a giant ball of chains hanging in the Magnan Projects space. Pseudo-chandeliers in art (pioneered by Petah Coyne) possess incumbent magnetism but this one also carries a disturbing mass. &lt;em&gt;Out to Lunch/Closed for the Day&lt;/em&gt; calls into question our reliance on safety codes and official inspections. The shiny metal coil (approximately a ton’s worth) approaches the structural limit of the chain’s strength to hold itself up. Pereda’s recurring strategy is to take things right up to the breaking point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/alejandro-almanza-pereda/hammer.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;hammer in fishtank&quot;&gt;
Courtesy of Magnan Emrich&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In another incredulous piece, atop a slender welded frame about ten feet high, perches a forty-gallon fish tank. In the water a host of red Christmas balls are tethered to a mallet, suspending it. The wooden handle floats up but the heavy head pulls down. In this sculpture, Pereda’s intense vision has moved literally from support to suspense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A holiday buoyancy is countered and re-channeled. Opposing equations co-exist. Sinking, flooding, and breaking are held in check but exert an ever-present pressure. Action is implied–specifically the possibility of the mallet smashing the bright ornaments or the glass tank. The contrast is paralleled by the opposing elements of air and water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a pair of serigraphs, Pereda echoes this balanced opposition. He depicts eggs in cartons, first on top of a scale and then underneath it. By placing the scale on top of the eggs, hope is threatened but reinforced. In Pereda’s art, we gasp as the normal order is reconvened in unexpected signals of renewal. The ephemeral parts of life hold up the concrete. The light holds up the dark and the heavy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remarking on his playful title, “The Fan and the Shit,” Pereda quipped that it was about the fans of art coming to admire his new shit. Art can be considered as the byproduct of mental digestion. This show presented some potent cerebral fertilizer.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Banksy Storms New York</title>
      <link>https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/banksy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2007 19:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://reviews.livemag.org/articles/end-run-19//articles/banksy/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Bankrobber Gallery, London&lt;br&gt;Vanina Holasek Gallery in Chelsea NYC&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every weekend there’s been a line outside one of the last quaint buildings left in the gallery district. The notoriously secretive Banksy is showing on all three floors of the Vanina Holasek Gallery. The windows are covered in American flags and Union Jacks with Victor rattraps attached. Other street artists, Pons and Elbow Toe have put up posters on the building and next door. A doorman with a clipped Brit accent, wearing a knee-length leather coat with a skull molded into it, allows you in. &lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crime tape and paintings left half-visible through bubble wrap immediately connotes an exhilirating sense of displacement. This ain’t your momma’s gallery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Banksy is an art legend. Sometimes called a guerrilla artist, he’s renowned for his hard-hitting political street art and museum escapades (he’s sneaked his own paintings into several museums). Yet he remains &lt;em&gt;muy&lt;/em&gt; elusive and reportedly no pictures of him have ever been released. Rumor had it that he was on the third floor at Vanina Holasek Gallery’s opening. Or he may have been in Bethlehem at another of his openings. He had been there to paint on and “through” the wall dividing Palestine and Israel.Banksy’s website said the New York show was unauthorized and “probably not worth seeing.” The Bethlehem show was authorized and also “probably not worth seeing.” Very funny. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Banksy slams icons together in a typically deconstructivist manner. A happy face peeks out from the grim reaper’s drooping hood. Soldiers keep guard while painting a peace sign on a wall. A masked urban guerilla pulls back his arm to hurl… a bouquet. The obvious appeal of clichés are challenged and forged anew.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/articles/banksy/dorothy.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;dorothy and trooper&quot;&gt;
Courtesy Vanina Holasek&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A jaguar busts out of its barcode cage and heads threateningly our way. This image is a metaphor for Banksy’s whole career in a way. It is the triumph of the wild spirit over the hegemony of civilization’s repression that makes Banksy a real hero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He cruds up the Queens the way Andres Serrano re-crucified Christ. Anachronisms and startling juxtapositions confront cultural disengagement. Hunters with spears stalk grocery shopping carts. Stripped down to the barest elements and presented in the starkest tones, the visual impact is huge. The aura and edge of street stencils give the works an aggressive and self-assured allure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The humor is more tongue in cheek than vicious: “Abandon Hope 9am to 5am.” Regardless, the point is made and hypocrites are targets. Banksy spares neither the power elites nor the die-hard radicals. A line of ragtag punks gathers to buy tee-shirts that proclaim “DESTROY CAPITALISM.” Actually, much of Banksy’s appeal is his punk aesthetic, polished as it is. There’s something irresistible about a chimp queen that screams Sex Pistols and shivers with defiant, raw energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Banksy is a lot like Delacroix’s Liberte&amp;acute; storming the barricade &amp;mdash; it’s hard not to get behind him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article first appeared in Chelsea Now&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>